Inventory of the W. H. (William Harold) Hutt Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Comments on an article by William Hutt, draft chapters, and notes, undated (Folder 18: 15)
- William Hutt, 1974-1984. (Folder 18: 16)
  Articles, clippings, newsletter, and press release about him. Includes review of his book, The Economics of the Colour Bar
- University of Cape Town, 1938-1964. (Folder 18: 17)
  Correspondence, letter to the editor, and a poem
- United States--Political, 1965-1985. (Folder 18: 18)
  Clippings
- Editorials of interest, 1985 (Folder 18: 19)
- Newspaper clippings, 1984 (Folder 18: 20)
- Miscellany, 1974-1980. (Box 18)
  Includes brochure, Congressional Record--Proceedings and debates of the 98th Congress, draft writings, letter, memorandum, and notes
- Letters to the editor and articles, Dallas Morning News, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 19: 1)
- Letters, invitation for biographical inclusion in the first volume of the International Who's Who of Intellectuals, postcard, and telegram to Frank Thompson, 1975 (Folder 19: 2)
- "Non-Market Influence on Incomes: Social Effects," William Hutt, undated. (Folder 19: 3)
  Includes foreword
- "Political Consequences of Twentieth Century Economic Policies" and "Unemployment Compensation,", undated. (Folder 19: 4)
  Articles by William Hutt
- "Note to Members of the National Taxation Limitation Committee" from William Hutt, undated (Folder 19: 5)
  (used in Labor Market). Includes related materials
- "Contractual Incomes under Market Determination," William Hutt, undated (Folder 19: 6)
- Tax--U.S.A., William Hutt, undated. (Folder 19: 7)
- List of major contributions—Articles, books, contents, index, and statistical data, 1975 (Folder 19: 8)
- Fragment of writings by William Hutt, undated (Folder 19: 9)
- Old newspaper clippings (unions), 1976 (Folder 19: 10)
- South Africa, 1985. (Folder 19: 11)
- Old correspondence--Friends in South Africa and of relevance to today's issues, 1973-1985 (Folder 19: 12)
- G. H. Godley, 1972-1982. (Folder 19: 13)
  Letters
- William Hutt--Personal file, 1982-1984. (Folder 19: 14)
  Includes certificate of appreciation for support from the Washington Legal Foundation, conference agenda, correspondence with Friedrich A. Hayek, letter to the editor by Edward Teller, memoranda, and newsletter
- Miscellany, 1965-1987. (Box 19)
  Includes articles by William Hutt, including "The Fiasco of Keynesian Policy" and others, bulletin, clippings, comments on the current South African situation, conference paper and final examination paper, Congressional Record, interview of William Hutt by Morgan O. Reynolds, journal, lecture by Malcolm Fisher, newsletter, reports, study, and teaching manual
- Old correspondence, 1965-1980. (Box-folder 20: 1)
  Includes fragments of writings and notes
- Miscellany, 1975-1980. (Folder 20: 2)
  Articles by others, list of Heritage Foundation publications, and draft writings on Keynes by William Hutt
- Unread mail, 1975. (Folder 20: 3)
  Letter
- Letter from Alastair Burnet and articles by Richard A. Viguerie and Henry A. Kissinger, 1971-1983 (Folder 20: 4)
- Article, clippings, correspondence, letter to the editor, list of personal belongings, memorandum, note, and receipt, 1962-1971 (Folder 20: 5)
- Correspondence, 1976-1982. (Folder 20: 6)
  Includes invitation and membership cards from National Advisory Council and Washington Legal Foundation, and newsletter
- B. C. Ziegler, 1977-1986. (Folder 20: 7)
  Flyers and brochures relating to investment
- Writings by others, 1931-1985. (Folder 20: 8-10)
  Includes pieces by Henry Regnery, Ayn Rand, and Wilhelm Röpke
- Sylvester Petro project, 1967-1978. (Box-folder 21: 1)
  Includes articles; clipping; papers submitted to the Mont Pelerin Society conference, Vichy, France; correspondence; list of papers available; newsletter; remarks; and schedule relating to the society's activities and the situation in Africa. Includes a paper by Arend Lijphart submitted to a conference on South African affairs
- Miscellany, 1948-1977. (Folder 21: 2)
  Includes address; articles, including one by Edward Teller on nuclear energy; book by Lester Thurow; comments on a paper on the economic consequences of changes in the structure of ownership in business firms; materials relating to education; proposal for creating an institute for private enterprise education research, University of Texas; lecture; minutes of meetings; and speech on public spending relating particularly to South Africa and the United States
- Material, 1973-1983. (Box 21)
  Agreement between William Hutt and the Liberty Fund for preparation of socio-economic projects; articles by others; correspondence; drafts of writings by William Hutt, including old manuscript materials; and newsletters relating to social, economic, and public policy issues
- Miscellany (Box 22)
  - "1963 June,", 1942-1964. (Folder 22: 1)
    Includes clippings and 1 photographic print depicting a lady standing in an open area facing a mountain range, undated
  - Correspondence, 1931-1965. (Folder 22: 2)
    Includes clippings, newsletter, and reviews by William Hutt
  - Excerpts on monopoly, undated. (Folder 22: 3)
    Miscellaneous articles and comments (of possible interest)
- Newspaper clippings, 1967-1969. (Folder 22: 4)
  Includes magazine, newsletter, notes, and report
- Draft chapters of "Say's Law," and "Unemployment Equilibrium Fallacy," and letter, 1964 and undated (Folder 22: 5)
- "The Nature of Sectional Gains,", undated. (Folder 22: 6)
  Drafts and notes
- Barbara E. Shenfield--Biographical outline, undated (Folder 22: 7)
- South Africa and Rhodesia, 1967-1977. (Folder 22: 8)
  Address, articles by William Hutt and others, clipping, digest, letter, memoranda, newsletter, notes, radio announcement, and statistical data
- South Africa--Apartheid and miscellaneous articles, 1970-1971. (Folder 22: 9)
  Clippings and South African Digest
- South Western Studies Institute, 1975. (Folder 22: 10)
  Minutes of a meeting
- The Strike-Threat System, undated. (Folder 22: 11)
  William Hutt's notes on the text
- University of Cape Town News, 1977-1978 (Folder 22: 12)
- World Research INK, 1978. (Folder 22: 13)
  Includes a letter
- United States Industrial Council, 1974-1978. (Folder 22: 14)
  Brochures, bulletin, flier, letter, newsletters, and press release
- Miscellany, 1964-1965. (Box 22)
  Includes articles, clippings, note to William Hutt, letter, list of guests for Hutt dinner, and memorandum
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 23)
  - "Economics for the Millions,", undated (Folder 23: 1-2)
  - "Executives' Qualities,", undated (Folder 23: 3)
  - "History of Monetary Ideas,", undated (Folder 23: 4)
  - "Keynes,", 1965 April 21 (Folder 23: 5-7)
  - Drafts of articles by William Hutt, undated (Folder 23: 8)
- Property code, 1942. (Folder 23: 9)
  Articles and letters
- South Africa except Cape Town, 1940. (Folder 23: 10)
  Article and memorandum
- Newspaper clippings, 1936-1956. (Folder 23: 11)
  Includes article, letter, and list of participants in lectures on political economy
- Income tax appeal, 1950-1951. (Folder 23: 12)
  Article, legal documents, and letter
- "The Gild System" by William Hutt, undated (Box-folder 24: 1)
- Correspondence
  - Old, 1963-1968. (Folder 24: 2)
    Includes agreement between William Hutt and Rampart College for employment, fragment of an article, and review of William Hutt's Economics and the Public
  - Miscellany, 1938-1968. (Folder 24: 3)
    Includes articles by William Hutt and others, letters, and related materials
- Article on South African economy, undated (Folder 24: 4)
- Articles by William Hutt relating to economic theories, liberalism, collective bargaining, laissez-faire, and situation in Rhodesia; clippings; deed of transfer; letter; and miscellany, 1938-1966 (Folder 24: 5)
- Correspondence, 1930-1967. (Folder 24: 6)
  Relates chiefly to Keynesianism and includes a fragment of William Hutt's writing
- Miscellany, 1959-1965. (Folder 24: 7-8)
  Includes agreement between William Hutt and the University of Cape Town regarding the publication of his book, The Theory of Collective Bargaining, articles by William Hutt and others, clippings, memorandum, notes, and telegram
- Articles by others relating to the conservatism of Adam Smith, end of neo-mercantilism, freedom and dissent, and role of government, undated. (Folder 24: 9)
  Includes notes by William Hutt
- Supplementary memorandum to the South African Shipping Commission by William Hutt, undated (Folder 24: 10)
- Draft writings by William Hutt about the work environment, labor relations, corporate policy, and related issues, undated (Box-folder 25: 1)
- South Africa--Research materials, 1949-1971. (Folder 25: 2)
  Includes clippings, letters, newsletters, and miscellany
- Review by M. Palyi of Keynesianism--Retrospect and Prospect, 1964 (Folder 25: 3)
- "Entrepreneurial Politics,", 1957-1962. (Folder 25: 4)
  Includes research monograph by Gordon Tullock and related conference papers
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1953-1967. (Folder 25: 5-6)
  Includes address, articles by William Hutt and others, clippings, conference paper, examination paper for a course in economics, letter, and newsletter
- John Rawls, 1966. (Folder 25: 7)
  Article and letters
- Remarks by William Hutt on the issues of freedom of speech in South Africa, undated (Folder 25: 8)
- Articles on poverty, development, and opulence, undated. (Folder 25: 9)
  Includes article by Milton Friedman and comments by William Hutt on Samuelson's economics
- William Hutt's comments on Samuelson's economics, undated (Folder 25: 10-13)
  Economics 218
  - "Twelve Thoughts on Inflation," article by William Hutt. (Folder 25: 14)
    Includes articles by others
  - "The Emancipation of Labor," article by A. A. Shenfield (Folder 25: 15)
- Address, William Hutt, Stanford University, Stanford, California, undated (Box-folder 26: 1)
- Theory of Collective Bargaining, 1975. (Folder 26: 2)
  Index, preface to the second edition, and postscript
- Writings by others, 1927-1976. (Folder 26: 3-4)
  Relates to Britain's future, economics and public policy, economic foreign policy of the United States, education, neo-colonialism, rural electrification, unemployment, wage laws, and other issues. Includes bulletin, journal, and reports
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 26)
  - "The Economics of Labor,", 1978 November 13
  - "Twelve Thoughts on Inflation,", 1965 [?].
    Includes foreword and postscript
  - "Problems of Reform and Transition in South Africa,", undated.
    Includes a cover letter to William Murchison, 1978 July 21
- Drafts relating to inflation, labor relations, strike threat, and related issues, undated
- Letters from William Hutt to R. F. Botha, Dan C. Heldman, Brian Kantor, and the editor, American Spectator, 1982-1983
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 27)
  - "Proportional Taxation, Equality and Freedom,", undated. (Folder 27: 1)
  - Drafts of William Hutt's writings, undated. (Folder 27: 2-3)
    Relates to Keynesianism, labor relations, race relations in South Africa, and related issues. Includes some biographical information
  - "Definitions," Appendix II, information about the author, and list of his publications, undated (Folder 27: 4)
  - "Equality and Equity in the Determination of Incomes and Taxes,", undated (Folder 27: 5)
  - "The Free Market" as providing a criterion for "The Just Price,", undated (Folder 27: 6)
  - "The Beneficence of the Competitive Process,", undated (Folder 27: 7)
  - "The Practical Working of the System I Advocate,", undated (Folder 27: 8)
  - "Justice in Taxation,", undated (Folder 27: 9)
  - "The Free Market as a Guarantor of Justice,", undated (Folder 27: 10)
  - "Proportional Voting,", undated (Folder 27: 11)
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship,", undated (Folder 27: 12)
  - "Prospects for Reform,", undated (Folder 27: 13)
  - "The Special Case of the Republic of South Africa,", undated (Folder 27: 14)
  - Appendices, I-III, undated. (Folder 27: 15-17)
    Includes information about Hutt, definitions, and list of selected contributions by William Hutt
- Article, journals, and reports by others relating to economic and social issues, 1950-1975 (Folder 27: 18)
- "The Exploitability of Investors," William Hutt, undated (Box 27)
- Biographical information about William Hutt and list of selected contributions by Hutt, undated
- Petro project, undated. (Box-folder 28: 1)
  Comments, list of chapters, introduction, and note
- Writings by William Hutt.
  Includes notes
  - "Economic Implications of Automation,", undated (Folder 28: 2)
  - "Some Basic Explanations,", undated (Folder 28: 3-5)
  - "Human Attributes: Envy and Acquisitiveness,", undated (Folder 28: 6-8)
  - "Bargaining,", undated (Folder 28: 9-11)
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship," preface and chapters, undated (Folder 28: 12-13)
  - "Labor's Disadvantage,", undated. (Folder 28: 14)
    Footnotes
  - Draft writings relating to labor policy, undated (Folder 28: 15)
  - Deregulation of aeronautics industry, undated (Folder 28: 16)
  - Old—Superseded, undated. (Folder 28: 17)
    Writings relating to the understanding of economic forces at work
  - "Equality and Equity: In the Determination of Incomes and Taxes,", undated. (Folder 28: 18)
    Photocopy
- Material, 1983 and undated. (Box 28)
  Includes letter from William Hutt to David M. Hart and a report, "Welfare and Poverty," National Center for Policy Analysis
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 29)
  - February (Folder 29: 1)
  - March (Folder 29: 2)
- William Hutt's writings
  - Unidentified chapter relating to proportional taxation, undated (Folder 29: 3)
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship,", undated. (Folder 29: 4-6)
    Foreword, introduction, chapter I, and some unidentified pages
  - Drafts about South Africa and Yugoslavia, free market system, principle of taxation and social justice, and related materials, undated (Box 29)
  - Vita, undated
  - "Proportional Taxation, Equality and Freedom,", undated
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship,", undated.
    Preface, chapters I and IV
  - "Co-Determination," "Principle of Social Justice," review of William Hutt's "Economists and the Public;" notes on "Some Neglected Issues in the Study of the So-Called 'Under-Developed Areas'," and miscellany, undated
- Teaching materials for William Hutt's classes (Box 30)
  - Economics courses.
    Includes lecture notes
    - Malthus, James Mill, Say, and Ricardo, undated (Folder 30: 1)
    - Alfred Marshall, undated (Folder 30: 2)
    - Karl Marx, undated (Folder 30: 3)
    - History of economic thought I
      - General, undated (Folder 30: 4-5)
      - Roman Philosophers, undated (Folder 30: 6-7)
      - Lecture notes including on Roman philosophers, undated (Folder 30: 8)
      - Unemployment equilibrium, undated (Folder 30: 9)
      - The Influence of Trade Unionism on J. S. Mill, undated (Folder 30: 10)
    - Mercantilism--Lectures, undated (Folder 30: 11)
- Writings by William Hutt
  - Draft chapter on economic history, undated (Folder 30: 12)
  - "The Free Market as a Criterion for the Just Price,", undated (Folder 30: 13-14)
  - "Fringe Benefits,", undated (Folder 30: 15)
  - "Labor's Share,", undated (Folder 30: 16)
  - "Empirical Studies of Labor's Share,", undated (Folder 30: 17)
  - Objections to the thesis--Preliminary discussion, undated (Folder 30: 18)
  - Preface, undated (Folder 30: 19)
  - "The Crucial Thesis,", undated (Folder 30: 20)
  - "The Employer Stereotype,", undated (Folder 30: 21)
  - "Exploitation of Labor,", undated. (Folder 30: 22-24)
  - Old materials about Keynesianism, undated (Folder 30: 25)
  - Foreword, undated (Box-folder 31: 1)
  - "Some Basic Explanations,", undated (Folder 31: 2)
  - "Human Attributes: Envy Acquisitiveness,", undated (Folder 31: 3)
  - "Bargaining,", undated (Folder 31: 4)
  - "The Non-Market Determination of Contractual Incomes,", undated (Folder 31: 5)
  - "Contractual Incomes under Market Determination,", undated (Folder 31: 6)
  - "Are Labor Unions Aristocracies?", undated (Folder 31: 7)
  - "The Neglected Victims,", undated (Folder 31: 8)
  - "Economizing Displacement,", undated (Folder 31: 9)
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship" and "The Sanctions for Managerial Command,", undated (Folder 31: 10-11)
  - "Democracy and Consumers' Sovereignty,", undated (Folder 31: 12)
  - "The Principle of Social Justice,", undated (Folder 31: 13)
  - "The Function of Losses and Profits,", undated (Folder 31: 14)
  - "Productivity and Wage Rates,", undated (Folder 31: 15)
  - "The Yugoslavian System,", undated (Folder 31: 16)
  - "Vision of a No-Strike Era,", undated. (Folder 31: 17)
    Conclusion
  - "The African People,", 1943. (Folder 31: 18)
    Article, clippings, and draft chapters
  - "Apartheid in South Africa and Its Foreign Critics,", undated (Folder 31: 19)
  - "The Organization Man,", undated (Folder 31: 20)
- Address changes, 1967. (Folder 31: 21)
  Includes correspondence, list, magazine, note, press comment on Rhodesia, and request for article
- "Trade Unions and the Price System," William Hutt, Mont Pelerin Society Conference, Seelisberg, Switzerland, 1949 July 4 (Folder 31: 22)
- South African correspondence, 1939-1944. (Folder 31: 23)
  Includes article and clippings
- Publishing agreements for Economists and the Public, 1936 February 12; The Theory of Idle Resources, 1939 February 13; and Non-Keynesian Economics, 1962 May 3. (Folder 31: 24)
  Includes photocopy of a letter to William Hutt
- Articles by others, 1972 and undated (Folder 31: 25)
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 32)
  - Keynesianis--Retrospect and Prospect, 1963. (Folder 32: 1-2)
    Includes miscellaneous Keynesian materials, undated
  - "The Free Choice of Gold as Currency,", undated (Folder 32: 3)
- Eirik G. Furubotn, 1982. (Folder 32: 4)
- "On Property Rights," Svetozar Pejovich and Eirik Furubotn, undated (Folder 32: 5)
- "Ludwig von Mises and the Market Process," L. M. Lachmann. (Folder 32: 6)
- Articles by others, conference program, newsletter, remarks, and review, 1980-1981. (Box 32)
  Relates to issues of monopoly, monetary control, medicine and the state, philosophy of human action, and usefulness of Minimum Wage Studies Commission
- William Hutt, 1975 and undated.
  Includes A Rehabilitation of Say's Law, "The Murder of a Color-Blind Democracy," and draft chapters and notes
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 33)
  - Keynesianism--Retrospect and Prospect, William Hutt, (1963)
    - Preface, undated (Folder 33: 1)
    - Prologue, undated (Folder 33: 2)
    - Chapters I-XVIII, undated (Folder 33: 3-20)
  - A Rehabilitation of Say's Law (1975), undated. (Folder 33: 21)
    Includes list of contents, preface, and chapters I-XVIII
  - Keynesianism, undated. (Box-folder 34: 1)
    Draft chapters
  - "The Closed Shop,", undated (Folder 34: 2)
  - "Kissinger's Prediction of a Political Crisis,", undated (Folder 34: 3)
  - Stuff for Keynesianism boon, undated. (Folder 34: 4)
    Notes
- Articles, conference papers, and lecture, 1962-1975. (Box 34)
  Relates to economic reform in Eastern Europe, education, gold standard, mining issues, monetary economics, property rights, and review of Keynesian economics
- Writings by William Hutt
- General, undated.
  Includes chapters on unemployment, Yeager's interpretation, and others
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 35)
  - "The Concept of the Free Market,", undated (Folder 35: 1)
  - "Knowledge and Decisions,", undated. (Folder 35: 2)
    Fragments of chapters I and II
  - History of Keynesianism, undated. (Folder 35: 3)
    Draft of writings
  - "The Roman Philosophers"--History of Economic Thought, undated (Folder 35: 4)
  - Draft chapters about Keynesianism, undated. (Folder 35: 5)
  - "The Free Market as a Criterion for the Just Price,", undated (Folder 35: 6)
  - "Equality and Equity,", undated (Folder 35: 7)
- Jeremy Bentham, undated. (Folder 35: 8)
  Article about him
- Material, 1971-1978. (Box 35)
  Includes articles by others including pieces by Milton Friedman and Peter Duignan. Relates to issues of colonialism, monetary policy, monopoly and free market economy, production and information costs, and related materials
- William Hutt's lectures, writings, and note (Box 36)
  - "The Relation between M'(d) and M'(C),", undated. (Folder 36: 1)
    (Econ 37)
  - "The Unemployment Equilibrium Fallacy,", undated (Folder 36: 2)
  - "The Expenditure Fallacy,", undated (Folder 36: 3)
  - "The Propensity to Consume and the Multiplier Fallacy,", undated (Folder 36: 4)
  - "The Accelerator Fallacy,", undated (Folder 36: 5)
  - Notes by William Hutt [?], undated (Folder 36: 6)
  - Say's Law
    - Drafts--Sections to omit, undated (Folder 36: 7)
    - A Rehabilitation of Say's Law--Drafts, undated (Folder 36: 8)
- Memorandum from LBY [?] to William Hutt regarding his paper on Patinkin, 1966. (Folder 36: 9)
  Includes notes from DB [?] on the "Demand for Money and the Rate of Interest," undated, and William Hutt's reply to LBY [?], 1967
- Writings by William Hutt
  - "Political Factor,", undated. (Folder 36: 10)
    Notes and draft writings
  - "The Role of Interest--Boom and Depression,", undated. (Folder 36: 11)
    Chapter from Keynesianism--Retrospect and Prospect [?]
  - "The Role of Interest Fallacy," Chapter XII from Keynesianism--Retrospect and Prospect [?]. (Folder 36: 12)
    Includes clipping
  - "Gold Slanders 2,", undated. (Folder 36: 13)
    Fragments
  - "Theory of Money"
    - Original copy, undated (Folder 36: 14)
    - History, undated (Folder 36: 15)
  - "International Money,", undated (Folder 36: 16)
  - "Central Banking--Institutional Analysis,", undated (Folder 36: 17)
  - Unidentified writings about credit expansion, inflation, and related issues, undated (Folder 36: 18)
- Articles, 1971. (Folder 36: 19)
  Includes "Hobart Paperback 1," by William Hutt and others, clippings on South Africa, letter relating to William Hutt's comments on prevailing left-liberal orthodoxy, review of writing by others, and miscellany
- Miscellany, 1966-1970 and undated. (Box 36)
  Includes
  - "Non-Keynesianism and Academic Freedom" by William Hutt; conference paper on interpretation of Keynes; comments on "The Inflation Outlook," by Charles B. Reeder, Paul A. Samuelson, and William S. Sneath; articles on money; and related materials
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 37)
  - "The Rate of Interest,", undated (Folder 37: 1)
  - Notes, undated (Folder 37: 2)
  - Draft chapters, 1951 and undated. (Folder 37: 3)
    Includes "The Moral Issue," "Keynes and Monetary Nationalism," "The Aftermath of War," "The Gold Standard and Orthodox Thought," and "Industrial Relation and the Industrial Council System"
  - "The Nature of Bank Credit System under the Gold Standard,", 1962 [?] (Folder 37: 4)
  - Unidentified drafts about credit expansion, gold standard, and related matters, undated (Folder 37: 5-6)
  - Draft writings about money, undated (Folder 37: 7)
  - Say's Law--History, undated (Folder 37: 8)
  - "Strike Warfare,", undated (Folder 37: 9)
  - "The Construction of the Administration Chart,", undated (Folder 37: 10)
  - "Where do We Go from Keynes?", undated. (Folder 37: 11)
    Includes articles by others and drafts
  - "Work Measurement and the Work Unit,", undated (Folder 37: 12)
- Material, 1966. (Box 37)
  Includes Mont Pelerin Society special meeting, Tokyo; list of papers; minutes; program; and speeches
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 38)
  - "The Great Depression,", undated (Folder 38: 1)
  - Notes, undated (Folder 38: 2)
  - "The Fed and the Feb,", undated. (Folder 38: 3)
    Includes articles by others, clippings, and drafts
  - A Rehabilitation of Say's Law, undated. (Folder 38: 4)
    Preliminary manuscripts
- Collected articles
  - M, 1955-1977 (Folder 38: 5-6)
  - N, 1954-1975 and undated (Folder 38: 7)
- Article, "It Can Be Done" by Arthur E. Morgan, 1959 (Box 38)